Finding Aid for New England Literature Program (University of Michigan) records, 1975-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
New England Literature Program (University of Michigan) records 1975-2005
University of Michigan. New England Literature Program.
1.0 linear ft.
0372 Bimu C26 2
The New England Literature Program, established in 1975, is a UM academic program based in Maine in which students and staff members live and work together closely, reading New England authors, writing, and exploring the New England countryside. The study of New England authors and culture is merged with other activities like camping, art, and canoeing. These records document the history of the program, and include correspondence, clippings, and journal anthologies.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 9170 ) was received in 2002.
The records are open for research.
The New England Literature Program (NELP) is a University of Michigan academic program that takes place at Camp Wohelo on Sebago Lake, Maine. Begun in 1975, and offered during the Spring half-term, students and staff members live and work together closely, reading New England authors, writing, and exploring the New England countryside, its people, culture, and history. The program was conceived by professors of English Walter Clark and Alan Howes.
In addition to formal academic work in literature and writing, non-credit instruction is given in canoeing, camping, art, and nature studies. Students teach or co-teach classes as part of their NELP experience. In addition, the program includes trips to places of natural and cultural interests, including several multi-day hiking and camping trips.
NELP offers creative writing workshops, but most writing is done in a journal. The journals are both personal and academic. Every NELP participant belongs to a journal group, which meets twice a week for discussion and sharing. Writing assignments of various sorts are connected with the readings, and they are supplemented by writing on topics of the students' own choosing. Student writing often explores creative expression, the natural world and the New England environment, and the writer's response to the NELP experience. For additional information, please consult the NELP website available (as of April 2003) at: http://www.lsa.umich.edu/english/nelp/whatisnelp.asp.
The records of the University of Michigan's New England Literature Program (NELP) covers the period from 1975 to 1998 and includes historical information, correspondence, and journal anthologies.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. New England Literature Program.; Creative writing.; Diaries--Authorship.; University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.; University of Michigan--Curricula.; University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.
- Historical Information
  The historical information includes general information about the program, along with newspaper clippings and a directory of students that were part of NELP during the period 1975 to 1983.
  - 1975-1983 (Box 1)
  - 1998 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The records also include correspondence regarding administrative issues, like funding and admissions, and letters from alumni. The latter gives researchers a sense of how positive and strong the program is for students.
  - Administrative, 1979 1984 1986 (Box 1)
  - Alumni, 1983-1986 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1987 1989 1990 (Box 1)
- Journal Anthologies
  The bulk of the material consists of journal anthologies. These anthologies compile excerpts from the journals written by the students during their program, and include writings, poems, and drawings.
  - 1976-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1980-1986, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - 1988-1991, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - 1997 (Box 1)
- Publications
  The two articles in the publications series were written by program co-founder Walter Clark describe the program. One of the articles was written for the book Teaching Environmental Program, and the other for the College of Literature, Science and Arts.
  - Article for the College of Literature, Science and Arts, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Article on Teaching Environmental Program, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Article in Michigan Daily, see October 13, 1974 issue (Box 1)
  - Article in Change Magazine, July 1976 (Box 1)
  - Article for the College of Literature, Science and Arts, Fall 2002 (Box 1)
- Program Materials
  The program materials consist of course packs, staff manuals and student/staff lists from various years.
  - Coursepacks
    - 1992 (Box 1)
    - 1996 (Box 1)
    - 2005 (Box 1)
  - Staff Materials
    - 2000 (Box 1)
    - 2005 (Box 1)
  - Student and Staff Lists
    - 2001, 2004, 2005 (Box 1)